Joel Worrall – Software Architect / Technology Leader

20 Hamlet Circle, Mechanicsburg, PA 17050 717.385.9970 – joel@joelworrall.com http://about.me/tangollama

Summary

Since 1999, I've been architecting and building great software and leading and motivating smart people to do great work. I've worked on every level of project and business problem: from consumer-facing apps and websites to multi-lingual, multi-national SaaS enterprise systems to transforming international nonprofits by leading the charge for the use of open source platforms. I've managed people. I've led teams. I've consulted at the highest and lowest levels. I've helped lead the turnaround of software companies in all facets: business, service, support, and product. I'm talented as an engineer and creative, and I know how to identify, recruit, and keep even better people to work with me and for me. I have experience managing off-shore and remote resources. I believe open systems produce wiser, sustainable, more profitable results, and I want to help organizations make good technology decisions as well as influence product, marketing, and messaging strategy.

Skills

General Skills

- A track record of creating, influencing and owning a vision for an organization
- Technical and organizational management of a software engineering department of 75 persons across 3 offices and 2 continents
- Team lead experience mentoring junior staff, teaching software architecture and web-based design, and overseeing requirements and design process
- Excellent oral and written communication skills
- Collaborative experience leading teams of designers, creatives, and UI/UX
- Conference and public speaking experience
- Resource and roadmap planning
- HR and personnel management
- Outsourcing expertise: offshore, local, and U. S. remote
- Significant consulting and customer facing / relationship management experience with small, medium, and fortune 500 corporate clients
- Highly self-motivated to improve and achieve corporate and personal success

Technical Skills Jumble

I'm proficient in all this technology and more. The bottom line is that I use technology as a tool to solve complex problems in the most elegant way possible.

HTML/JavaScript, SQL/PLSQL, PHP, XSLT/XPath/XML, Ruby/Rails*, C/C++/C#*, ASP*, OS X, Unix, Linux, Windows, Joomla, Wordpress, Google Apps, Exchange, LDAP, Apache, IIS, NGINX, Oracle, Postgres, MySql, J2EE Application/Servlet Containers, CVS, SVN, Ant, Cruise Control, JUnit, JMeter, Eclipse, NetBeans, MS Visual Studio, JQuery, EXT, Java (Servlets, JDBC, JSP, Custom Taglibs, JSTL, JCE, JavaMail, JAXP, JDOM, GLUE / Electric XML, EJB, RMI, JMS, AWT, JNDI, Swing*, Java Logging, Log4J, Java Imaging API, Struts, Maverick, Spring, Hibernate, JavaRosa, J2ME, i18n)

Experience

Education

BA – Computer Science, Messiah College, Grantham, PA MAR – Old Testament, Evangelical Theological Seminary, Myerstown, PA (part time)

Recognition/Awards

Pixel Awards 2011: Best Nonprofit Website (pixelawards.com/nom_win_2011.php) ComputerWorld Honors Recipient 2012: CUREkids (cure.org/curekids) Best Lightning Talk Speaker: 2012 Business of Software Conference

Employment

<u>Chief Technology Officer and acting Vice President of Marketing</u> – May 2013 to present CURE International / Lemoyne, PA

- Senior management team of a 1,600 employee international organization with board-level reporting responsibilities
- Lead the technology, marketing, and creative efforts of CURE International
- Oversee the operational and fundraising technology strategy for a network of 27+ countries
- Leading a movement for nonprofits to use Wordpress as a platform for communications and fundraising, and contributing code back to Wordpress for those purposes
- Represent the technology leadership of CURE and its mission to partners and donors
- Oversaw the release of the CUREkids App for iPhone and Android (cure.org/app)

<u>Vice President of Technology</u> – October 2009 to May 2013 CURE International / Lemoyne, PA

- Invented, architected, built, deployed, and oversee the world's first non-profit real-time patient reporting and crowd-sourced funding system, CUREkids (cure.org/curekids) delivering real-time feedback on procedures in CURE hospitals, resulting in millions of dollars in annual operational donations from small, mid-range, and major donors
- Influence messaging, marketing, and communication for all levels of donor engagement
- Responsible for all creative support services for the organization: video, print, online
- Cultivate strategic relationships to support marketing and fundraising
- Oversee partnership programs with music artists, churches, campuses, and businesses
- Developed web-based tools to create a next-generation online donor engagement experience using MySQL, JQuery, HTML, CSS, Javascript, PHP, Wordpress, SOAP, and API's from Facebook, Google, Twitter, and Google Apps
- Oversaw transitioned from Blackbaud Raiser's Edge to Salesforce.com
- Migrated CURE's global employee email Exchange Server to Google Apps for Nonprofits

<u>President / Senior Consultant</u> – May 2009 to Present Java Brewery, Inc / Mechanicsburg, PA

■ Engaged in outsourced product development, technical management, strategic

- partnerships, technology & market research, and technical leadership
- Providing recruiting services, partnerships, and technology due diligence

<u>Vice President, Engineering & Development</u> – March 2009 to October 2009 *Mzinga / Burlington, MA and Mechanicsburg, PA*

- Responsible for technology roadmap, partner selection, R&D, and all engineering staffing (FTE, contract, partner, and outsourcing): a 40-person department
- Led architecture and delivery of Mzinga's first release of OmniSocial product
- Provided technical face and leadership through a monumental debt re-structuring and re-capitalization
- Led shift of Mzinga's product architecture and business model from Application Service Provider to complete SaaS multi-tenant, single instance environment
- Guided the organization through the merger of three separate companies and development organizations as well as the incorporation of offshore, outsourced team

<u>Director of Engineering</u> – August 2008 to March 2009

Mzinga / Burlington, MA and Mechanicsburg, PA

- Promoted to acting director of software engineering, simultaneously managing teams and projects in Mechanicsburg and Boston offices, including necessary business travel
- Involved in the overarching corporate product strategy for Mzinga's Social Learning and Social Media suites
- Charged with the release planning and execution for two different SaaS platforms in two different technology stacks (Oracle/Java and SQLServer/.NET), combining team members from both offices as well as offshore, outsourced resources

<u>Director of Development, Learning & Workplace Communities</u> – Feb. 2008 to Aug. 2008 *Mzinga / Burlington, MA and Mechanicsburg, PA*

- Promoted to director of engineering for learning & workplace communities: feature development, sustaining engineering & support, enterprise customization consulting, and future technology and architecture
- Leading technical and business efforts to move traditional hosted software model to multi-tenant Software as a Service architecture
- Integrating learning platform with social media platform to deliver Mzinga's new Social Learning Suite
- Negotiated major software vendor contracts and services

<u>Development Manager</u> – Feb. 2007 to Feb. 2008

Knowledgeplanet (Mzinga) / Burlington, MA and Mechanicsburg, PA

- Promoted to manager of engineering for enterprise-class, hosted LMS
- Developed and managing corporate outsourcing strategy with offshore outsourcing partner to provide variable staffing and focus engineering resources on innovation
- Performed technical diligence in acquisition of the Prospero Social Media platform
- Implemented lightweight, effective performance review and project scheduling

Software Architect – July 2006 to Jan. 2007

Knowledgeplanet / Mechanicsburg, PA

■ Joined the engineering organization after an extended consulting contract to be part

- of the successful launch of the 6.7 version of the Knowledgeplanet LMS
- Architected LMS reporting framework using Actuate, Resin, Java 1.5, and Oracle
- Served as consultant and solution architect, working with troubled client relationships
- Coordinated department-wide training in vendor-specific technologies
- Managed outsourced, off-shore development with two separate partners in India, creating the organization's outsourcing and development orientation processes

Principal / Senior Consultant – April 2003 to Jan. 2007

Java Brewery, Inc / Mechanicsburg, PA

- Built a software / solutions business that successfully executed over \$700,000 of contracts over a 3-year period
- Possessed expertise in portal and web service architectures and frameworks
- Served as technical liaison and interim managing engineer for multiple organizations seeking to build development teams, conducting training, head-hunting, and technical specification assistance
- Analyzed company data models and performed data architecture and database design and implementation services
- Provided requirements and design analysis and documentation
- Engaged in website design and content management deployments for small and medium-sized businesses

<u>Lead Java Developer and Chief Architect</u> – July 2000 to April 2003 *CommNav, Inc / Mechanicsburg, PA*

- Responsible for approving designs and documentation, overseeing and mentoring junior developers, and managing testing for all CommNav Java development efforts
- Architected, designed, and led development of the CommNav Java Portal infrastructure and the CommNav Java applications using, object oriented methodology and J2EE Resin technology, including an extensive custom Taglibs
- Primary author of the development API's and system documentation for the CommNav Java Portal infrastructure
- Developed multiple browser-based applications, including content management, flexible role-based and object security, message forums, a Single Sign On framework, document management systems using WebDAV, and web mail supporting both POP3 and IMAP using the JavaMail API

<u>Software Engineer</u> – May 1999 to July 2000 *KnowledgePlanet, Inc / Mechanicsburg, PA*

- Designed and implemented browser-based J2EE applications and features for the KnowledgePlanet Learning Management System, running on JRun application server and an Oracle database, using JSP, Servlets, Java, SQL, and XML/XSL
- Created a XML-based transaction management system
- Evaluated load and functional testing software, taking part in the purchasing of the automated testing package for KnowledgePlanet's development organization

Interests

International Travel, Software Development Methodology and Process, Israel and the Ancient Near East, academic writing, teaching, U2, Cleveland Browns, software solutions for non-profit organizations